Register of the George Wolfgang Felix Hallgarten Papers, 1874-1975
Hoover Institution Archives
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1937-1975
  - Das Wettruesten: Seine Geschichte bis zur Gegenwart (The arms race: Its history up to the present), 1967
    - Unpublished English version
      - First draft entitled "Twilight of Man? A Short History of the Arms Race in This Century," 1965 (?)
        - Part I. Carbon copy and photocopy
        - Part II. Carbon copy and photocopy (Box 21)
      - Second draft entitled "A Short History of Arms Race in This Century," 1967 (?)
        - Chapter 12. Photocopy of typescript
      - Fourth draft entitled "Twilight of Man?" A Short History of the Arms Race in Modern Times," 1974
        - Part I. Photocopy of typescript
        - Part II. Photocopy of typescript
        - Part IIIA. Photocopy of typescript (Box 22)
        - Part IIIB. Photocopy of typescript
        - Prospectus and table of contents. Photocopy of transcript
        - Fragments, n.d. Typescript
        - Fragments, n.d. Holograph and related newspaper clippings
  - Why Dictators? The Causes and Forms of Tyrannical Rule Since 600 B.C., 1954
    - First draft entitled "Soziologie der Diktatur" (Sociology of dictatorship, 1937. Basis for the work
      - Fragment, in German. Pages 196-326. Typescript
      - Synopsis, in German. Typescript
      - Partial translation into English by Constance Hallgarten (1881-1969), mother of author
      - Part I. Typescript
      - Part II. Two handwritten notebooks
      - Part III. Two handwritten notebooks
    - Second draft entitled "Sociology of Dictatorship: The Causes and Forms of Tyrannical Rule in the Past and Present," 1952 (Box 23)
      - Parts I and II. Annotated typescript
      - Parts III and IV. Annotated typescript
      - Project synopsis. History of Hallgarten's work on the book from the 1930s to 1950s. Typescript and carbon copy
      - Letter to Alfred A. Knopf, Ltd. Carbon copy
      - Publicity and reviews. Mimeographed copies and newspaper clippings
      - Letter from Albert Einstein, June 22, 1954, praising the work. Letter translated into English. Carbon copy of typescript
  - Lectures and articles
    - "Adolf Hitler and German Heavy Industry 1931-1933: A Discussion of the Relations between Politics and Economics in Recent German History," 1952. Journal of Economic History, Vol. XII, Nr. 3. Typescript (draft entitled with dates 1918-1933)
    - "Adolf Hitler and German Heavy Industry 1918-1933," 1952. Research notes for the above article in German and English. Typescript and holographic notes
    - "Adolf Hitler und die deutsche Schwerindustrie" (Adolf Hitler and German Heavy Industry), 1953. Magazine article for Links. Printed copy
    - "After Fifty Years...Reflections on the Outbreak of the First World War," 1964. Lecture. Typescript
    - "Aktenanhang: Zur Politik von Hugo Stinnes 1922-1923" (Appendix of documents concerning the policies of Hugo Stinnes 1922-1923), n.d. Carbon copy of typescript
    - "The Arms Race After 1945 in the Light of History," 1965. Lecture delivered in New Delhi, India. Typescript of lecture and printed copy of review
    - Asahi Journal interview, 1965, n.t. Discussion of imperialism in English
    - "The Backstage Story of the War," July 5, 1940. Lecture for the Commonwealth Club, San Francisco. Two mimeographed copies
    - "Behind Britain's Armament Lag," December 11, 1938. The San Francisco Chronicle. Newspaper clipping
    - Bismarck, n.d., n.t. Lecture (?) for symposium at Brown University. Holographic and typescript notes in German and English
    - "Can We Prevent That Crime?" The Youth of 20th Century Dictators," n.d. Typescript synopsis
    - "Darf Krupp auf Fascisten schiessen?" (May Krupp shoot at fascists?), July 8, 1938, Pariser Tageszeitung. Newspaper clipping
    - "Disraeli," n.d. Holographic lecture notes
    - "Does Ridicule Kill Dictators?" n.d. Typescript synopsis
    - "Das Eindringen deutschen Kapitals in Suedangole am Ende des 19. Jahrhunderts" (The influx of German capital into South Angola at the end of the nineteenth century), n.d. Carbon copy of typescript and reprints of related articles (Box 24)
    - "Der Einfluss der totalen Diktaturen auf die Demokratie in den U.S.A." (The influence of totalitarianism on the democracy in the U.S.A.), n.d. Lecture. Typescript
    - "Die Entwicklung der Friedensidee in der neuren Zeit: Ein Bericht in Dokumenten" (The development of the concept of peace in recent history: A report in documents), 1963 (?). Carbon copy of typescript
    - "European Diplomatic History," 1970-1971. Lectures for the University of Dayton
      - Part I. Holographic and typescript notes
      - Part II. Holographic and typescript notes
    - "European History," 1971. Lectures for History 414, University of Dayton. Holographic and typescript notes, and teaching evaluations
    - "Die Formen der Herrschaft in den Entwicklungsgebieten im Licht der Max Weberschen Soziologie" (Types of rule in the developing areas in the light of Max Weber's sociology), 1967 (?). University lecture. Typescript
    - "Formen und Schicksal der Diktaturen nach dem zweiten Weltkrieg" (The forms of dictatorship and their fate after the Second World War), 1967. Typescript and holographic notes
    - "Die Frage der Schuld am ersten Weltkrieg: Einst und heute" (The question of guilt for the First World War: Previously and today), n.d. Typescript
    - "Fremdheitskomplex und Uebernationalismus" (Alienation complex and super-nationalism), 1938. Zeitschrift fuer freie deutsche Forschung. Reprint
    - "Gedanken zum Koelner Vortrag" (Ideas for the Cologne lecture), n.d. Holographic notes (Box 25)
    - "Germany Arms the Turks," n.d. Carbon copy of typescript
    - "The Germany of 1914 and 1937: A Survey of the Development of Modern Imperialism," 1937. Two mimeographed copies
    - "Die geschichtlichen Wirkungen der wirtschaftlichen Konjunkturschwankungen seit 1870" (The historical effects of economic reverses since 1870), n.d. Annotated typescript
    - "Die gesellschaftsgeschichtlichen Hintergruende der beiden Weltkriege" (The socio-historical background of the two world wars), 1965. Lecture. Typescript and publicity
    - "Heinrich Himmler's Childhood: Comments by an Eyewitness," 1969 (?). Typescript
    - "History of Imperialism 1870-1945," n.d. Holographic and typescript notes
    - "History of Modern Dictatorship," 1972. Lecture for the University of North Carolina, Charlotte. Typescript and holographic notes, clippings, examinations, statement on Viet Nam, and photocopy of newspaper clipping
    - "Hitler's Next Moves," May 19, 1940. The San Francisco Chronicle. Newspaper clipping
    - "Imperialism After World War II," n.d. Lecture. Photocopy of typescript
    - "Imperialismus," n.d. Entry for unidentified encyclopedia, in German. Annotated galley proof
    - "Der Imperialismus in Vergangenheit und Gegenwart" (Imperialism in the past and present), 1958. Lecture. Carbon copy of typescript, newspaper reviews, ticket, and publicity
    - "The Influence of the U.S. Constitution upon Germany's Constitutional Thinking, Especially on Her War-Making Power," n.d. Carbon copy of typescript
    - "Kommt eine neue Zeit Starker Maenner?" (Will there be a new age of strong men?), 1965 (?). Lecture. Typescript
    - "Die Leidensgeschichte der Abruestungsidee seit der Ersten Haager Friedenskonferenz" (The painful history of the idea of disarmament since the first peace conference in the Hague), 1958. Typescript and two mimeographed copies of lecture for radio, and newspaper review
    - Letter to the editor of the Washington Post, September 9, 1954. "After EDC--What?" Newspaper clipping
    - Letter to the editor of the Washington Post, January 1959. "Josephus and Jesus," in response to letter by Rabbi Martin S. Halpern of December 23, 1959, together with Halpern's reply to Hallgarten. Newspaper clippings
    - Letter to the editor of the Washington Post, August 18, 1959. Reply to Hallgarten letter by Lawrence A. Perkins, "Leftism in Cuba." Newspaper clipping
    - Letter to the editor of the Journal of Modern History, June 1960, n.t. Information about Himmler. Photocopy
    - "Max Webers Soziologie: Ein Handwerkzeug des Geschichtsschreibers" (Max Weber's Sociology: A tool for the historian), 1967 (?). Lecture, University of Munich. Holographic and typescript notes
    - "Mein Mitschueler Himmler" (My classmate Himmler), October 14, 1961. Nuernberger Nachrichten. Newspaper clipping
    - "Mein Schulfreund Himmler!" (My school friend Himmler!), August 7, 1961. NRZ. Newspaper clipping
    - "Milady Conquers Arabia: Rise, Fall and Transformation of Hester Lucy Stanhope," n.d. Transcript (Box 26)
    - "Moderne Befreiungsdiktatoren und Proletarier-Fuehrer: Ein Dreigespraech" (Modern liberationist dictators and proletarian leaders: A conversation about politics and Stalin. Fragmentary typescript
    - Munich lectures, 1950. Notes untitled
      - "Die Entstehung der Diktatur: Vergleichende geschichtliche Untersuchung der Gewaltherrschaften vom Altertum bis zur Gegenwart" (The origin of dictatorship: A comparative historical examination of rule by force from antiquity to the present) (?). Typescript and holographic notes
      - "Uebungen zur internationalen Politik der europaeischen Kabinette 1890-1940" (Seminar on the international policies of the European cabinet 1890-1940) (?). Seminar notes, list of participants, letter of appreciation from the Bavarian Ministry of Education, and notice in the newspaper
    - Munich lectures, 1967 (?), n.t. Pacifism. Typescript and holographic notes in German and English, list of guests
    - "Nach fuenfzig Jahren: Deutsche Geschichte als Schluessel zu den Weltkriegen" (After fifty years: German history as the key to the world wars), n.d. Carbon copy of typescript
    - "Neues Material zur Geschichte des Imperialismus vor 1914" (New material about the history of imperialism before 1914), n.d. Lecture, University of Vienna. Holographic notes
    - "Our Policy in Germany and the Case of Krupp," n.d. Annotated typescript
    - "The Present World Situation and the Problem of Dictatorship," n.d. Lecture. Typescript
    - "The Problem of European Unity Since the First World War, 1965. Lecture. Typescript
    - "Protestantism and the Reunification of Germany," 1957. Lecture. Typescript
    - "The Quartermaster General's Procurement During World War I in Reference to the U.S. Small Business Man," n.d. Carbon copy of typescript fragment
    - "Reflections on the Arms Race Since 1918," 1972 (?). Lecture, Lexington, Kentucky. Holographic and typescript notes and clippings
    - Review of Deutschland und China im 19. Jahrhundert (Germany and China in the nineteenth century) by Helmuth Stoecker. American Historical Review, July 1959. Printed copy
    - Review of Elites against Democracy by Walter Struve, n.d. Carbon copy of typescript
    - Review of Erinnerungen (Memoirs) by Albert Speer. The Maryland Historian, 1971 (?). Photocopy
    - Review of Eugene Etienne und die franzoesische Kolonialpolitik (Eugene Etienne and the French colonial policy) by Herward Sieberg and Die Nordwestgrenze in der Verteidigung Indiens (The Northwest border in the defense of India) by Horst Jaeckel. American Historical Review, October 1969
    - Review of Grossunternehmer und Tyrann (Entrepreneur and tyrant) by Louis Lochner. Geist und Tat, July 1955. Printed copy
    - Review of Die Internationale Politik edited by Arnold Bergstraesser. American Historical Review, October 1958
    - Review of Der Primat der Innenpolitik (The primacy of domestic policy) by Eckart Kehr. Deutsche Literaturzeitung, November 1967. Two reprints and carbon copy of typescript
    - Review of Unternehmer gegen Monopole (Entrepreneurs against monopolies) by Helga Nussbaum. American Historical Review, December 1967
    - Review of Vneshniaia politika I diplomatiia germanskogo imperialisma v kontse XIX veka (Foreign policy and diplomacy of German imperialism at the end of the nineteenth century) by A. S. Yerusalimskii, n.d. Carbon copy of typescript
    - "Richard Wagner, Adolf Hitler and Their Messiah-Complex," n.d. Typescript
    - "Die Rolle der Arbeiterbewegung in Europa und in den Vereinigten Staaten: Parallelen und Unterschiede" (The role of the labor movement in Europe and the United States: Parallels and differences), 1958. Lecture. Typescript, newspaper reviews, invitations, and publicity
    - "Die Rolle der internationalen Ruestung" (The role of international armament), September 4, 1964, Die Zeit. Printed copy
    - "Der Ruestungswettlauf nach dem Zweiten Weltkrieg" (The arms race after World War II), n.d. Lecture. Carbon copy of typescript
    - "Die Schule der Faschisten" (School for fascists), n.d. Satire. Carbon copy of typescript and two leaves of older version called "Schule der Diktatur" (School of dictatorship) (Box 27)
    - "The Secret Behind Hitler's Russian War," n.d. Typescript
    - "The Social Foundations of Pacifism and Appeasement from Cromwell to Hitler," 1962 (?). Typescript and notes
    - "The Social Foundations of the German Armaments Policy," March 1937, The Contemporary Review. Printed copy
    - "The Social Foundations of World War Strategy," 1940. Lecture, Pacific Coast Branch of the American Historical Association. Typescript
    - "The Sociological Aspects of the Arms Race After 1945," 1969 (?). Photocopy of typescript
    - "Some Comments on the Sociological Forms of Dictatorship Since the Climax of Fascism," 1973. Lecture given in Japan. Carbon copy of typescript
    - "The 'Sphinx' Behind the Screen of the Weimar Republic: The Political Game of General Hans von Seeckt 1919-1926," 1947 (?). Published in abridged form as "General von Seeckt and Russia 1920-1922" in Journal of Modern History vol. XXI, no. 1, 1949. Carbon copy of typescript, holographic notes in German, newspaper clipping
    - "Statement Made During the March of University of Dayton Members in the Matters of Vietnam and the Calley Affair, 1971. Two photocopies of typescript
    - "Tantalus in Japan," 1965 (?). Carbon copy of typescript
    - "That Monster Was My Classmate: The Strange Transformation of Little Heinrich Himmler into Hitler's #1 Henchman," 1954 (?). Carbon copy of transcript
    - "U.S. Policy and the Question of German Rearmament, Especially in the Economic Field," n.d. Carbon copy of typescript
    - "Die Vereinigten Staaten und die Gesellschaftskrise in Latein Amerika" (The United States and the Social Crisis in Latin America), 1965. Lecture. Carbon copy of typescript and newspaper review
    - "Das Verhaeltnis zwischen Bank- und Industrie-kapital in der Deutschen Aussenpolitik der Wilhelminischen Aera" (The relationship between bank and industry capital in German foreign policy of the Wilhelmine era), 1938, VIIIe Congrès International des Sciences Historiques. Reprints and photocopy of responses by Veit Valentin et al.
    - "Warum nur 14 Jahre? Die Weimarer Republik: Erforschtes und Erlebtes" (Why only fourteen years? The Weimar Republic: Research and experience), 1958. Carbon copy of typescript, newspaper reviews, and publicity
    - "Was Adolf Hitler of Jewish Descent?" n.d. Carbon copy and typescript
    - "Wer brachte Hitler an die Macht? Neues Licht durch Dokumente" (Who brought Hitler to power? New light from documentation), n.d. Article includes transcriptions of correspondence by Franz von Pappen, Kurt Lersner, Kurt von Schroeder, Wilhelm Keppler, etc. Typescript and carbon copy
    - "Der Wettlauf der Grossmaechte um Afrika" (The rivalry of the big powers for Africa), 1958. Lecture. Carbon copy of typescript, newspaper reviews, invitation, and publicity
    - "Das Wettruesten nach dem Zweiten Weltkrieg" (The arms race after the Second World War), n.d. Lecture. Typescript
    - "What I Saw in Germany Fifty Years Ago: In Commemoration of the Outbreak of World War I (August 1, 1914)," 1964. Carbon copy of typescript
    - "What Made de Gaulle and Adenauer Click? Ventures and Common Thoughts of the Champions of Europe," n.d. Two typescript versions
    - "What the United Nations Hit: KRUPP," n.d. Typescript
    - "When Will Germany Collapse?" 1942. Lecture. Mimeographed copy
    - "Who and What Made Pan-Europe Fashionable?" 1963. Typescript and carbon copy of article, synopsis, and correspondence about possible publication
    - "Who Loaded the 'Guns of August'?" n.d. Typescript of synopsis
    - "Why Dictators?" n.d. Three different versions of lecture. Typescript and publicity
    - "William II and Adolf Hitler Celebrate Anniversaries," n.d. Typescript
    - "Zum 22. Januar 1958" (On the 22nd of January 1958). Poem dedicated to Hallgarten's nanny, nicknamed Loeffel
    - "Zur Geschichte der Abruestung im 20. Jahrhundert" (On the history of disarmament in the twentieth century), 1960, Zeitschrift fuer Politik
    - "Zur Geschichte der Vietnam Krise" (On the history of the Vietnam crisis), n.d. Typescript, holographic notes, and newspaper clippings
  - Research notes (Box 28)
    - Abetz, Otto, n.d. Holographic notes in German on book by Abetz, entitled Das offene Problem (The open problem)
    - "Adelsanbetung und Deutschlands Geschick" (Workship of royalty and the fate of Germany), n.d. Holographic and typescript notes in German and English
    - Africa, 1968. Typescript notes in German
    - American political history, n.d. Holographic and typescript notes in English and newspaper clippings
    - Bismark, n.d. Holographic in German
    - Colonialism, n.d. Holographic notes in German and English
    - Disarmament and the arms race, n.d. Miscellaneous holographic notes in English
    - "Einiges Material ueber die Auslands Organization" (Some material on the foreign organization of the Nazi party), n.d. Holographic notes in German
    - "Griechenland" (Greece), n.d. Typescript notes in German
    - Lenin and Keynes, n.d. Holographic notes in German
    - "Mussolini," n.d. Holographic notes in German
    - Nazi High Command, n.d. Holographic notes in German
    - "RADAR," n.d. Holographic notes in German
    - South America, n.d. Holographic notes in German and English
    - "Stalin," n.d. Holographic notes in German and English
    - Sternberg, Fritz, n.d. Carbon copy of typescript notes in English
    - Tolstoy, n.d. Holographic notes in English in same notebook with comments on World War II
    - "Totalitarian War and its Consequences," n.d. Miscellaneous typescript notes in English
    - Viet Nam, n.d. Holographic notes in English and related newspaper clippings
    - Wagner-Nietzsche case, n.d. Holographic and typescript notes in German and English, photocopy of printed letter by Thomas Mann on the subject
    - "Zaire," 1975. Typescript notes in French
    - Miscellany. Various holographic and typescript notes in German and English
  - Research proposals (Box 29)
    - "The Attitude of Industry Toward Politics," 1974. AHA Newsletter, April 1974. Printed and mimeographed copies of proposal and related correspondence
    - "The Chances of Success of International Detentes," 1974. Photocopy of application to Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars, and related correspondence
    - "Establishment of an Institute for Sociological Research on International Affairs Since 1919," 1954. Two carbon copies of application to Ford and Rockefeller Foundations, and related correspondence
    - "The Fate of Imperialism Since the 1870s," 1971. Research project at Antioch College. Typescript and related correspondence
    - "Max Weber's Sociology as a Tool in the Hands of the Historian," 1969. Two photocopies of transcript and holograph
    - "Study and Use of Captured German Records," 1959. Proposal to B'nai B'rith Antidefamation League. Carbon copy of typescript
    - "A Study of the Social Background of European Power Politics 1919-1945," 1955. Two carbon copies of typescript and related correspondence
  - Film scripts and synopses
    - "End of Humanity? Ideas for a Film on the Past and Possible Future of the International Arms Race," 1974
      - General
      - First draft. Annotated typescript
      - Second draft. Carbon copy of typescript
      - Third draft. Typescript and photocopy
    - "The Fifth Pyramid: The Secret of the Leopold Amherst Papyrus," n.d. Two carbon copies of typescript
    - "Heavy Water: The Nations' Pace for the Atom-Splitter," n.d. Typescript and carbon copy. Three typescript copies of synopsis
    - "Louis Napoleon: The Career of a Dictator," n.d. Carbon copy of typescript
    - "Six Feet Above Ground," n.d. Two carbon copies of typescript
    - "Suez Canal: Life and Fall of a Great Promoter" (Ferdinand de Lesseps), n.d. Two carbon copies of typescript
- MICROFILM
  - Microfilm cabinet "General von Seeckt, Adolf Hitler und die deutsche Schwerindustrie" (General von Seeckt, Adolf Hitler and German heavy industry), n.d. Typescript of essay by Hallgarten (Microfilm-cabinet Microfilm cabinet)
  - Railway question, 1875-1881. Documents from the Vienna National Archives relating to the construction of railways to the Middle East. Handwritten and typescript copies